<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-11-07T08:54:35-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mateo Dulce Rubio</title><author><name>Mateo Dulce Rubio</name><email>mdulceru@andrew.cmu.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Victimization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/victimization" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Victimization" /><published>2023-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/victimization</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/victimization">&lt;h1 id=&quot;effects-of-adolescent-victimization-on-offending-flexible-methods-for-missing-data--unmeasured-confounding&quot;&gt;Effects of Adolescent Victimization on Offending: Flexible Methods for Missing Data &amp;amp; Unmeasured Confounding&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mdulcer.github.io&quot;&gt;Mateo Dulce Rubio&lt;/a&gt;,
  

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ehkennedy.com/&quot;&gt;Edward H. Kennedy&lt;/a&gt;,
  

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rscj.newark.rutgers.edu/people/faculty/dr-valerio-bacak/&quot;&gt;Valerio Baćak (Rutgers)&lt;/a&gt;,
  

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.heinz.cmu.edu/faculty-research/profiles/nagin-daniel&quot;&gt;Daniel S. Nagin&lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;single&quot; src=&quot;/images/papers/heterogeneous_all.png&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;single&quot;&gt;
      Heterogeneous ATT of victimization on future offending by age at the victimizing event using doubly robust estimators.


    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The causal link between victimization and violence later in life is largely
accepted but has been understudied for victimized adolescents. In this work
we use the Add Health dataset, the largest nationally representative longitudinal survey of adolescents, to estimate the relationship between victimization and future offending in this population. To accomplish this, we derive a
new doubly robust estimator for the average treatment effect on the treated
(ATT) when the treatment and outcome are not always observed. We then
find that the offending rate among victimized individuals would have been
3.86 percentage points lower if none of them had been victimized (95% CI:
[0.28, 7.45]). This contributes positive evidence of a causal effect of victimization on future offending among adolescents. We further present statistical
evidence of heterogeneous effects by age, under which the ATT decreases
according to the age at which victimization is experienced. We then devise
a novel risk-ratio-based sensitivity analysis and conclude that our results are
robust to modest unmeasured confounding. Finally, we show that the found
effect is mainly driven by non-violent offending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

	&lt;strong&gt;Effects of Adolescent Victimization on Offending: Flexible Methods for Missing Data &amp;amp; Unmeasured Confounding&lt;/strong&gt;


&lt;br /&gt;


	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mdulcer.github.io&quot;&gt;Mateo Dulce Rubio&lt;/a&gt;,
	

	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ehkennedy.com/&quot;&gt;Edward H. Kennedy&lt;/a&gt;,
	

	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rscj.newark.rutgers.edu/people/faculty/dr-valerio-bacak/&quot;&gt;Valerio Baćak (Rutgers)&lt;/a&gt;,
	

	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.heinz.cmu.edu/faculty-research/profiles/nagin-daniel&quot;&gt;Daniel S. Nagin&lt;/a&gt;
	


&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;span class=&quot;cv-description&quot;&gt;
	
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;

--&gt;

&lt;i&gt;arXiv:2309.12595 (arXiv).  2023.&lt;/i&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;


	&lt;span class=&quot;pub-misc&quot;&gt;

	

	&lt;!--
	  &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/victimization&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-link&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Project
	  &lt;/a&gt;
	--&gt;

	

	
	  &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2309.12595.pdf&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;i class=&quot;far fa-file-pdf&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; PDF
	  &lt;/a&gt;
	

	

	

	

	

	

	
	&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6P81u2h30mA&quot;&gt;
		&lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-video&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Presentación en español
	&lt;/a&gt;
	

	

	

	

	

	

	
		
		
	

	

	
	
	&lt;/span&gt;







&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ## BibTeX
```
@misc{dulce2023effects,
  title={Effects of Adolescent Victimization on Offending: Flexible Methods for Missing Data &amp; Unmeasured Confounding}, 
  author={Dulce Rubio, Mateo and Kennedy, Edward H. and Baćak, Valerio and Nagin, Daniel S.},
  year={2023},
  eprint={2309.12595},
  archivePrefix={arXiv},
  primaryClass={stat.ME}
}

``` --&gt;</content><author><name>Mateo Dulce Rubio</name><email>mdulceru@andrew.cmu.edu</email></author><summary type="html">Effects of Adolescent Victimization on Offending: Flexible Methods for Missing Data &amp;amp; Unmeasured Confounding Mateo Dulce Rubio, Edward H. Kennedy, Valerio Baćak (Rutgers), Daniel S. Nagin Heterogeneous ATT of victimization on future offending by age at the victimizing event using doubly robust estimators. Abstract The causal link between victimization and violence later in life is largely accepted but has been understudied for victimized adolescents. In this work we use the Add Health dataset, the largest nationally representative longitudinal survey of adolescents, to estimate the relationship between victimization and future offending in this population. To accomplish this, we derive a new doubly robust estimator for the average treatment effect on the treated (ATT) when the treatment and outcome are not always observed. We then find that the offending rate among victimized individuals would have been 3.86 percentage points lower if none of them had been victimized (95% CI: [0.28, 7.45]). This contributes positive evidence of a causal effect of victimization on future offending among adolescents. We further present statistical evidence of heterogeneous effects by age, under which the ATT decreases according to the age at which victimization is experienced. We then devise a novel risk-ratio-based sensitivity analysis and conclude that our results are robust to modest unmeasured confounding. Finally, we show that the found effect is mainly driven by non-violent offending. Reference Effects of Adolescent Victimization on Offending: Flexible Methods for Missing Data &amp;amp; Unmeasured Confounding Mateo Dulce Rubio, Edward H. Kennedy, Valerio Baćak (Rutgers), Daniel S. Nagin arXiv:2309.12595 (arXiv). 2023. PDF Presentación en español</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reland</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/reland" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reland" /><published>2023-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/reland</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/reland">&lt;h1 id=&quot;reland-risk-estimation-of-landmines-via-interpretable-invariant-risk-minimization&quot;&gt;RELand: Risk Estimation of Landmines via Interpretable Invariant Risk Minimization&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mdulcer.github.io&quot;&gt;Mateo Dulce Rubio&lt;/a&gt;*,
  

  
    
Siqi Zeng*,
  

  
    
Qi Wang,
  

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/didier-alvarado-engineer/&quot;&gt;Didier Alvarado (UNMAS)&lt;/a&gt;,
  

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/francisco-moreno-rivera-8159179b/?originalSubdomain=co&quot;&gt;Francisco Moreno (CCCM)&lt;/a&gt;,
  

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.cmu.edu/~hheidari/&quot;&gt;Hoda Heidari&lt;/a&gt;,
  

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;https://feifang.info/&quot;&gt;Fei Fang&lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;single&quot; src=&quot;/images/papers/23-reland-vis.png&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;single&quot;&gt;
      Integration of RELand system into the humanitarian demining pipeline. Current non-technical surveys (grey) are based on the visual inspection of data in geospatial information systems and human expert analyses including local community surveys and domain knowledge. RELand (yellow dashed box) serves as an additional toolbox that contains three major components: dataset enhancement based on existing public geospatial datasets (red), risk modeling with machine learning methods (blue), and interactive web interface (green).

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Landmines remain a threat to war-affected communities for years after conflicts have ended, partly due to the laborious
nature of demining tasks. Humanitarian demining operations begin by collecting relevant information from the sites to be
cleared, which is then analyzed by human experts to determine the potential risk of remaining landmines. In this paper, we
propose RELand system to support these tasks, which consists of three major components. We (1) provide general feature
engineering and label assigning guidelines to enhance datasets for landmine risk modeling, which are widely applicable
to global demining routines, (2) formulate landmine presence as a classification problem and design a novel interpretable
model based on sparse feature masking and invariant risk minimization, and run extensive evaluation under proper protocols
that resemble real-world demining operations to show a significant improvement over the state-of-the-art, and (3) build
an interactive web interface to suggest priority areas for demining organizations. We are currently collaborating with a
humanitarian demining NGO in Colombia that is using our system as part of their field operations in two areas recently
prioritized for demining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

	&lt;strong&gt;RELand: Risk Estimation of Landmines via Interpretable Invariant Risk Minimization&lt;/strong&gt;


&lt;br /&gt;


	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mdulcer.github.io&quot;&gt;Mateo Dulce Rubio&lt;/a&gt;*,
	

	
		
Siqi Zeng*,
	

	
		
Qi Wang,
	

	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/didier-alvarado-engineer/&quot;&gt;Didier Alvarado (UNMAS)&lt;/a&gt;,
	

	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/francisco-moreno-rivera-8159179b/?originalSubdomain=co&quot;&gt;Francisco Moreno (CCCM)&lt;/a&gt;,
	

	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.cmu.edu/~hheidari/&quot;&gt;Hoda Heidari&lt;/a&gt;,
	

	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;https://feifang.info/&quot;&gt;Fei Fang&lt;/a&gt;
	


&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;span class=&quot;cv-description&quot;&gt;
	ML system to support humanitarian demining, currently being tested in Colombia.
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;

--&gt;

&lt;i&gt;Forthcoming (Forthcoming).  2023.&lt;/i&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;


	&lt;span class=&quot;pub-misc&quot;&gt;

	

	&lt;!--
	  &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/reland&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-link&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Project
	  &lt;/a&gt;
	--&gt;

	

	
	  &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.03115.pdf&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;i class=&quot;far fa-file-pdf&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; PDF
	  &lt;/a&gt;
	

	

	

	

	

	

	
	&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/live/cKINGMf4R2c?si=ERclLIqUps2K90-b&quot;&gt;
		&lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-video&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Presentación en español
	&lt;/a&gt;
	

	

	

	

	

	

	

	

	
	    &lt;span style=&quot;color: #9a9a9a&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-asterisk&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; --&gt; * Authors contributed equally&lt;/span&gt;
	
	
	&lt;/span&gt;




&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ## BibTeX
```


``` --&gt;</content><author><name>Mateo Dulce Rubio</name><email>mdulceru@andrew.cmu.edu</email></author><summary type="html">RELand: Risk Estimation of Landmines via Interpretable Invariant Risk Minimization Mateo Dulce Rubio*, Siqi Zeng*, Qi Wang, Didier Alvarado (UNMAS), Francisco Moreno (CCCM), Hoda Heidari, Fei Fang Integration of RELand system into the humanitarian demining pipeline. Current non-technical surveys (grey) are based on the visual inspection of data in geospatial information systems and human expert analyses including local community surveys and domain knowledge. RELand (yellow dashed box) serves as an additional toolbox that contains three major components: dataset enhancement based on existing public geospatial datasets (red), risk modeling with machine learning methods (blue), and interactive web interface (green). Abstract Landmines remain a threat to war-affected communities for years after conflicts have ended, partly due to the laborious nature of demining tasks. Humanitarian demining operations begin by collecting relevant information from the sites to be cleared, which is then analyzed by human experts to determine the potential risk of remaining landmines. In this paper, we propose RELand system to support these tasks, which consists of three major components. We (1) provide general feature engineering and label assigning guidelines to enhance datasets for landmine risk modeling, which are widely applicable to global demining routines, (2) formulate landmine presence as a classification problem and design a novel interpretable model based on sparse feature masking and invariant risk minimization, and run extensive evaluation under proper protocols that resemble real-world demining operations to show a significant improvement over the state-of-the-art, and (3) build an interactive web interface to suggest priority areas for demining organizations. We are currently collaborating with a humanitarian demining NGO in Colombia that is using our system as part of their field operations in two areas recently prioritized for demining. Reference RELand: Risk Estimation of Landmines via Interpretable Invariant Risk Minimization Mateo Dulce Rubio*, Siqi Zeng*, Qi Wang, Didier Alvarado (UNMAS), Francisco Moreno (CCCM), Hoda Heidari, Fei Fang Forthcoming (Forthcoming). 2023. PDF Presentación en español * Authors contributed equally</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rexperiments</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/rexperiments" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rexperiments" /><published>2023-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/rexperiments</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/rexperiments">&lt;h1 id=&quot;randomized-experiments&quot;&gt;Randomized Experiments&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.cmu.edu/~acoston/&quot;&gt;Amanda Coston&lt;/a&gt;,
  

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mdulcer.github.io&quot;&gt;Mateo Dulce Rubio&lt;/a&gt;,
  

  
    
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ehkennedy.com/&quot;&gt;Edward H. Kennedy&lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;single&quot; src=&quot;/images/papers/ai4si.png&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;single&quot;&gt;
      AI for Social Impact Book. Edited by Milind Tambe, Fei Fang &amp;amp; Bryan Wilder. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ai4sibook.org/&quot;&gt; https://ai4sibook.org/ &lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once deployed in the real world, even the most carefully designed artificial intelligence (AI) systems may fail to achieve their intended goals or may have adverse unintended consequences. 
How should researchers assess whether the AI actually improved outcomes? Randomized experiments are the gold standard for evaluation. They enable one to isolate the effect of the AI from other 
potentially confounding factors. Examples of AI systems for social impact that have been deployed and evaluated in the real world abound: Wang et al. [2019] studies the effect on the adenoma detection 
rate of using real-time AI-assisted colonoscopies, Mohler et al. [2015] evaluates the effect of using a predictive policing model on crime rates in Los Angeles, Mate et al. [2021] assesses the effect 
on dropout of using a model to prioritize the follow-up of participants in a maternal and child care information program, etc. In this chapter we give an introduction and review of randomized experiments. 
More details and exposition can be found in Hernán and Robins [2010], Imbens and Rubin [2015], Rosenbaum [2002], Tsiatis [2006], van der Laan and Robins [2003], for example, among many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

	&lt;strong&gt;Randomized Experiments&lt;/strong&gt;


&lt;br /&gt;


	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.cmu.edu/~acoston/&quot;&gt;Amanda Coston&lt;/a&gt;,
	

	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mdulcer.github.io&quot;&gt;Mateo Dulce Rubio&lt;/a&gt;,
	

	
		
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ehkennedy.com/&quot;&gt;Edward H. Kennedy&lt;/a&gt;
	


&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;span class=&quot;cv-description&quot;&gt;
	AI for Social Impact Book. Edited by Milind Tambe, Fei Fang &amp; Bryan Wilder. &lt;a href=&apos;https://ai4sibook.org/&apos;&gt; https://ai4sibook.org/ &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;

--&gt;

&lt;i&gt;AI for Social Impact Book (AI4SI Book).  2022.&lt;/i&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;


	&lt;span class=&quot;pub-misc&quot;&gt;

	

	&lt;!--
	  &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/rexperiments&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-link&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Project
	  &lt;/a&gt;
	--&gt;

	

	
	  &lt;a href=&quot;https://ai4sibook.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/randomized-experiments.pdf&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;i class=&quot;far fa-file-pdf&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; PDF
	  &lt;/a&gt;
	

	

	

	

	

	

	

	

	

	

	

	

	

	

	
	
	&lt;/span&gt;




&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ## BibTeX
```


``` --&gt;</content><author><name>Mateo Dulce Rubio</name><email>mdulceru@andrew.cmu.edu</email></author><summary type="html">Randomized Experiments Amanda Coston, Mateo Dulce Rubio, Edward H. Kennedy AI for Social Impact Book. Edited by Milind Tambe, Fei Fang &amp;amp; Bryan Wilder. https://ai4sibook.org/ Abstract Once deployed in the real world, even the most carefully designed artificial intelligence (AI) systems may fail to achieve their intended goals or may have adverse unintended consequences. How should researchers assess whether the AI actually improved outcomes? Randomized experiments are the gold standard for evaluation. They enable one to isolate the effect of the AI from other potentially confounding factors. Examples of AI systems for social impact that have been deployed and evaluated in the real world abound: Wang et al. [2019] studies the effect on the adenoma detection rate of using real-time AI-assisted colonoscopies, Mohler et al. [2015] evaluates the effect of using a predictive policing model on crime rates in Los Angeles, Mate et al. [2021] assesses the effect on dropout of using a model to prioritize the follow-up of participants in a maternal and child care information program, etc. In this chapter we give an introduction and review of randomized experiments. More details and exposition can be found in Hernán and Robins [2010], Imbens and Rubin [2015], Rosenbaum [2002], Tsiatis [2006], van der Laan and Robins [2003], for example, among many others. Reference Randomized Experiments Amanda Coston, Mateo Dulce Rubio, Edward H. Kennedy AI for Social Impact Book (AI4SI Book). 2022. PDF</summary></entry></feed>